Guide to the Eugenia Saville Papers, circa 1950-1977
Duke University. University Archives
Eugenia Saville papers circa 1950-1977
Duke University. University Archives
Saville, Eugenia Curtis, 1913-2006
3 linear feet Extent: 1,000 Items
Eugenia Seville joined the faculty of the Duke University Music Department in 1947 as an instructor, and was eventually promoted to Assistant and Associate Professor in 1950 and 1960, respectively. She specialized in Italian sacred music, and directed the Duke Madrigal Singers from 1947 to 1972. She died in 2006. Contains course materials, music facsimiles, performance scores, materials related to the Duke Madrigal Singers, personal correspondence, and ephemera accumulated during Saville's research trips in the U.S. and Europe.
UA.29.02.0106
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The Eugenia Saville Papers were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 2005.
Biographical Note
Eugenia Seville was born in Clinton, Pennsylvania. She received her B.M. from New Jersey State Teachers' College in 1934 and her M.A. in Musicology from Columbia University in 1942. Between 1952 and 1958, she undertook advanced work in musicology at the University of North Carolina. She joined the faculty of the Duke University Music Department in 1947 as an instructor, and was eventually promoted to Assistant and Associate Professor in 1950 and 1960, respectively. She specialized in Italian sacred music, and directed the Duke Madrigal Singers from 1947 to 1972. She died in 2006.
Collection Overview
Contains materials from Saville's various courses taught at Duke. Also includes facsimiles of musical manuscripts, and vocal parts for music used as class examples and as part of the Madrigal Singers' performance repertoire. Collection also contains a wooden box of lantern slides and negatives, primarily of scenes from historical opera performances and opera houses. Removed rubber-bands, 1 folder of receipts and photocopy requests, 1 folder of student employment records, 1 folder of salary information and peripheral "to do" lists.
Subject Headings
Duke University. Dept. of Music; Duke University -- Faculty; Lantern slides; Saville, Eugenia Curtis, 1913-2006
Related Material
Music (Dept. of) Sound Recordings, 1956-1990.
University Archives. Duke University.
Allan H. Bone Papers, 1944-1989.
University Archives. Duke University.
A. Hollis Edens Records, 1949-1960.
University Archives. Duke University.
Mildred L. Hendrix papers, 1951-1968.
University Archives. Duke University.
Contents of Collection
- Container List, 3 Boxes
  - Correspondence, Photo (Box 1)
  - Mass Incipits (For Class Examples) (Box 1)
  - Mass Incipits (For Class Examples) (Box 1)
  - Mass Incipits (For Class Examples) (Box 1)
  - [Liturgical Exercises] (Box 1)
  - [Liturgical Music, Class Notes] (Box 1)
  - Liturgical Index (Box 1)
  - Pistoia Mass Materials, Class Exercises (Box 1)
  - RC M147 [Mass Materials] (Box 1)
  - Complete Mass [Class Examples] (Box 1)
  - Fitzwilliam 2F2 [Class Materials] (Box 1)
  - 2 Credos (Box 1)
  - Requiem [Parts, Notes, Facsimiles] (Box 1)
  - RC M147 Missa (Box 1)
  - Pisa I-IV (Box 1)
  - Pistoia II, Roll II (Box 1)
  - Pistoia 194-5 (Box 1)
  - G.C.M. Clari, Op. 1, Edited by E. Saville (Box 1)
  - Scales - Exercises (Box 1)
  - Renaissance Madrigal Course (Bibliographies, Projects, Seminar) (Box 1)
  - Medieval-Renaissance (Bibliographies, Histories, Course Outlines, Quizzes) (Box 1)
  - Acoustics, Aesthetics, Psychology (Box 1)
  - Art: 1850-Contemporary (Box 1)
  - 17th Century Preview (Box 1)
  - Essential Terms and Concepts, Quizzes (Box 1)
  - Music 125: "Listen" Work-Book (Box 1)
  - Music 125 [Course Materials] (Box 1)
  - Monteverdi's Orfeo, Act II (Box 1)
  - Primitive Music [Bibliographies, Example Syllabi, Course Materials] (Box 1)
  - Greek Classics - Henderson Course (Box 1)
  - Medieval Music (Box 2)
  - Baroque Instrumental (Box 2)
  - Theory, 1973-74 (Box 2)
  - Baroque Music (Box 2)
  - Study Aids, Master File and Working Versions (Box 2)
  - Undergraduate Faculty Council Report, Curriculum Subcommittee, 1968 (Box 2)
  - Liturgical Index: Latest (Box 2)
  - Liturgical Index: Working Versions, Papers, Directions, etc. (Box 2)
  - "Golden Oldies" [Course Materials] (Box 2)
  - Bloesch Magnificat (Box 2)
  - Smither, "A History of the Oratorio," c.1977 (Box 2)
  - Giovanni Clari Biography (Box 2)
  - City Lists (Box 2)
  - Wooden box of negatives [Opera houses, Operatic Scenes] (Box 2)
  - City Lists, cont'd (Box 3)
  - [Copy of Saville's 18th Century Vocal Duets Publication] (Box 3)
  - Appendices and Inventories (Box 3)
  - Ordinary and Proper Settings (Box 3)
  - Bloesch Magnificat (Box 3)
  - Emily Boyd Lowe Material (Box 3)
  - Newspaper Clippings, Correspondence, Programs (Box 3)
  - Student Pageant (Box 3)
  - Graduate Study in Music - Early Approaches (Box 3)
  - American Musicological Society, 1971 (Box 3)
  - Julia Mueller Memorial, 1977 (Box 3)
  - University Council on Research (Box 3)
  - Personal Correspondence (Box 3)
  - Duke University Research Council (Box 3)
  - Lectures and Program Notes (Box 3)
  - Sabbaticals (Box 3)
  - Trowbridge Review (Box 3)
  - Music Department Faculty Memos, Madrigal Singers Files (Box 3)
  - Shirley Verrett File (Box 3)
  - Older University Education Ideas (Box 3)
  - Undergraduate Studies (Box 3)
  - Research Grant Material (Box 3)
  - Seminar/Library Communication (Box 3)
  - University Faculty Committee (Box 3)
  - Family Letters from Pakistan (Box 3)
  - Arts Center Committee (Box 3)
  - Vatielli - Storia della Musica (Box 3)